In this clean, orderly, disciplined world, who
needs guys like McMurphy? Everybody.
One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest is a drama film directed by Miloš Forman.
A petty criminal fakes insanity to serve his sentence
in a mental ward rather than prison.
He soon finds himself as a leader to the other patients—and an enemy
to the cruel, domineering nurse who runs the ward.
Randle Patrick McMurphy, played by Jack Nicholson.
Billy Bibbit, played by Brad Dourif.
Nurse Mildred Ratched, played by Louise Fletcher.
Martini, played by Danny DeVito.
Dale Harding, played by William Redfield.
Orderly Turkle, played by Scatman Crothers.
One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest is a 1975 American psychological comedy-drama film
directed by Miloš Forman, based on the 1962 novel of the same name by Ken Kesey.
The film stars Jack Nicholson as a new patient at a mental
institution and Louise Fletcher as the abusive head nurse.
Will Sampson, Danny DeVito, Sydney Lassick, William Redfield, Christopher Lloyd, and Brad
Dourif play supporting roles, with the latter two making their feature-film debuts.
Originally announced in 1962 with Kirk Douglas
starring, the film took 13 years to develop.
Filming finally began in January 1975 and lasted three months, on location in Salem,
Oregon, and the surrounding area, and in Depoe Bay on the north Oregon coast.
The producers shot the film in the Oregon State Hospital, an actual
psychiatric hospital, which is also the novel's setting.
The hospital is still in operation, though the original
buildings in the film have been demolished.
The film was released on November 19, 1975.
One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest received critical acclaim and is considered by
critics and audiences to be one of the greatest films ever made.
It is the second of three films to win all five major Academy Awards (Best Picture, Best Actor, Best Actress, Best Director, and
Best Adapted Screenplay) following It Happened One Night (1934) and preceding 1991's The Silence of the Lambs.
It won numerous Golden Globe and BAFTA Awards.
In 1993, the film was deemed "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant" by the United
States Library of Congress and selected for preservation in the National Film Registry.
Additionally, One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest was ranked number 33 on
the American Film Institute's updated 100 Years...
100 Movies list in 2007.
The film explores themes of mentally disabled, friendship,
based on novel or book, nurse, lunatic asylum.
The tone is emotional.